Jonah 3
And the word of the LORD came unto Jonah the second time, saying,
Arise, go unto Nineveh, that great city, and preach unto it the preaching that I bid thee.
So Jonah arose, and went unto Nineveh, according to the word of the LORD.
Now Nineveh was an exceeding great city of three days' journey.
And Jonah began to enter into the city a day's journey, and he cried, and said,
Yet forty days, and Nineveh shall be overthrown.
Jonah had no choice.
He had to proclaim the word he received from God.
Nor did the people of Nineveh have any choice: they had to listen to Jonah's preaching.
But notice what kind of reception that judgment sermon gets.
The chapter continues as follows:
So the people of Nineveh believed God, and proclaimed a fast, and put on sackcloth, from the greatest of them even to the least of them.
For word came unto the king of Nineveh, and he arose from his throne, and he laid his robe from him, and covered him with sackcloth, and sat in ashes.
So Jonah preached the law of God in the city of Nineveh, and
the people reacted to it by believing it to be true and in horror.
When the men from the smallest to the greatest proclaimed a fast,
there's already the first part of repentance present and at hand.
Which is a frightened conscience.
That is, that man understands that he cannot stand and is not worthy before God.
Things are really bad: if God judges a man well and rightly, it will go badly for him.
But it must also be said in connection with the proclamation of the fast of the men of Nineveh:
would there be a reason to proclaim a fast in your own life, around you, or even in our country?
Not because there is any merit in that fast,
but it helps to humble yourself.
It helps to feel your own condition before God better.
For word came unto the king of Nineveh,
and he arose from his throne, and he laid his robe from him, and covered him with sackcloth, and sat in ashes.
And he caused it to be proclaimed and published through Nineveh
by the decree of the king and his nobles, saying,
Let neither man nor beast, herd nor flock, taste any thing: let them not feed, nor drink water:
But let man and beast be covered with sackcloth, and cry mightily unto God:
yea, let them turn every one from his evil way, and from the violence that is in their hands.
Who can tell if God will turn and repent, and turn away from his fierce anger, that we perish not?
That’s quite a fast.
First, the people from the smallest to the greatest proclaimed the fast.
And then the king seals that it is the official fast of the kingdom or the city.
Such a reaction to the preaching of the law is good.
No one in the nation considered it insignificant that God designated an unpleasant sermon for them.
But they would react to it soon if, however, God were still merciful.
And that's what Christian conversion and repentance is:
The first part is when the sermon of God’s law frightens the conscience.
And the other part is when God comforts with the remission of sins, and the man believes it.
And so that second part is also immediately present for the Ninevites in here. Namely:
And God saw their works, that they turned from their evil way; and God repented of the evil, that he had said that he would do unto them; and he did it not.
2 Chronicles 7:14 says:
If my people, which are called by my name, shall humble themselves, and pray, and seek my face,
and turn from their wicked ways; then will I hear from heaven, and will forgive their sin,
and will heal their land.
This has come true many times during world history.
There have been many times when the people have been openly wicked and godless.
And then once again God has let to preach
God's law which horrifies
and the Gospel which comforts.
And God saw their works, that they turned from their evil way;
and God repented of the evil, that he had said that he would do unto them; and he did it not.
Nineveh was destroyed later.
The generation that repented received grace.
Lamentations 3:22–23 says this:
It is of the LORD'S mercies that we are not consumed, because his compassions fail not.
They are new every morning: great is thy faithfulness.